Empresses in the Palace—the Legend of Zhen Huan
Adopted from the novel by Liu Lian Zi
[contact translators] carsenwei@yahoo.com
[subscribe on homepage] liberapay.com/ZHZSubbers
Theme: Unfortunate Love
Perturbed by the thoughts on my mind
no matter how hard I try to sever my love.
I could give away my crown for the beauty by my side,
but the wheel of fortune turns weals into woes,
and woes into weals.
No one is the master of their own destiny,
the vicissitudes throughout their life.
For the lovers of all time,
who can break the spell of romance?
I could give away my crown for the beauty by my side,
but the wheel of fortune turns weal into woe,
No one is the master of their own destiny,
the vicissitudes throughout their life.
For the lovers of all time,
who can break the spell of romance?
Who can break the spell of romance?
[contact translators] carsenwei@yahoo.com
[subscribe on homepage] liberapay.com/ZHZSubbers
Jiang Zhongmin is very competent.
Everything has been well-placed in a blink.
My Lady, did you vindicate yourself last night?
I hope His Majesty no longer believes you were
involved in Meizhuang's feigned pregnancy.
I cannot predict what thoughts cross His Majesty's mind.
I simply did what I was supposed to do.
I would never wish to get into his bad graces.
I see. When you are in His Majesty's good graces
My Lady, he cares who is disturbing you.
That's why he punished Huang Guiquan.
His Majesty must have resolved all his doubts in you, My Lady.
I hope so.
As long as His Majesty trusts you, My Lady.
Your Majesty, Jiang Zhongmin from
the Household Department is here.
Show him in.
Your Majesty, only three boxes of
Persian Brow Ink were offered as tribute this year.
Unlike the past years when twenty boxes were offered,
it is insufficient to provide for all the concubines.
I hope Your Majesty can enlighten my dull-witted mind
as to how we will distribute the three boxes.
Why do you have to ask me over such a trivial matter?
When there is "too little congee for all the monks",
Your Majesty's reward will prevent conflicts among the concubines.
You have an agile mind for your new job.
The Empress will have one box
as the distinguished head of the harem.
Lady Sourire is gorgeous when she draws
her eyebrows as "distant mountains". She'll have one.
As for the third box ...
I like my eyebrows without using ink pens.
Your Majesty need not think of me.
Consort Fleur likes to draw her eyebrows
long into the temples. I'll give it to her.
The other concubines may use Bronze Ink.
You deserve my reward of a box of Persian Ink
to thank you for telling me that Shen was
almost poisoned and preventing disorder in the harem.
Your Majesty agreed to not commit it to your memory.
What is there to thank me for?
Your Highness, here is the Persian Ink of this year.
I have always received three boxes of Persian Ink.
Why is there only one box for this year?
The Household Department said that only three boxes
were offered as tribute this year due to low production.
What about the other two boxes?
One was rewarded to the Empress,
and the other for Lady Sourire.
Zhen Huan! That bitch again!
What a minx to have seduced His Majesty away last night
holding me up to ridicule by that wretch Astuce!
And now she dares to take away my Persion Ink!
The Empress was rewarded as a matter of formality.
Zhen Huan is nothing!
May peace be restored in Your Highness
for the good of Your Highness' health.
Your Highness, we can develop a plan rather than a rage.
What is the plan?
I will think of a plan to allay the worries of Your Highness.
A mere Noble Lady was able to take down Huang Guangquan.
What is there for you to plan now?
It took your best efforts to get rid of Shen Meizhuang.
Zhen Huan was not only unaffected but is rising.
I would not risk placing confidence in you.
Your Highness has eyes like mirrors that see my loyalty
for the good graces Your Highness bestowed on me.
That I know.
Otherwise you wouldn't have a place in the palace.
It was not easy to regain His Majesty's favor.
I am not to be harmed by a wretch.
Qinmo, why did you not come with the princess?
Does she only visit His Majesty?
Wenyi hasn't been sleeping well lately.
She hasn't been outside for two days
except visiting His Majesty in the afternoon.
It is an exception for you as a mere Noble Lady to be allowed to raise the Imperial Heir.
It is also inconvenient to take care of her in your chamber.
You Highness...
She'll have a speedy recovery living in my palace.
Your Highness, Wenyi cries at night
and will really disturb your sleep.
I can bring her here anytime as Your Highness pleases.
Bring the princess here.
Her nursemaid will stay here as well.
Yes.
What's wrong? Are you afraid that I would harm the princess?
I dare not think that way.
I am immensely grateful that ...
Your Highness adores and cares for Wenyi.
Very well.
You must remember that the princess would
have been kept in the Imperial nursery if it were not for me.
You would not have been able to live with her.
Yes.
When she's in my care, you will have enough time
to think about what you can do for me.
I understand, Your Highness.
It is rather cold at night.
I wonder if Meizhuang is well provided for.
A garment on a cold day is a simple gift but warm.
Meizhuang will be warmed to her heart when she receives it.
Your delicate embroidery will bring it to perfection.
My Lady, the Household Department brought you
a box of Persian Ink that His Majesty rewarded.
His Majesty likes your eyebrows drawn as "distant mountains".
Place it over there.
My Lady, you may want to try some.
It is a very precious gift.
I heard that the Persian Ink is worth thousands of taels.
It is my first time seeing it.
Sourire, you should try it on.
I'll take care of the embroidery.
Madam Orchid fulfilled what you requested of her.
She also brought a note from Meizhuang
that must be handed to you, My Lady.
Take care of yourself and aid Lingrong.
Meizhuang is still considerate of me despite her difficult situation.
My Lady, she is right.
Companion An is the only one you can rely on at the moment.
Song Zhi, why are you not using the parasol for the princess?
I am.
But she has still been exposed to the sun.
Just a little bit. We'll be indoors shortly.
Song Zhi, the princess is young and delicate...
I know that.
But she's very blessed to be taken care of by Her Highness.
My Lady, why do you seem unthankful
for Her Highness's good grace?
It's not like that, Madam.
My Lady is more than happy that Her Highness
would like to take care of the princess.
My Lady was just showing her motherly care ...
All right, Her Highness is waiting for us.
Let's go quickly.
My Lady, we cannot show defiance to Her Highness.
I've always been obedient to her and contributed to her efforts.
But now she's taking away my daughter!
I've been living under her eaves and by her command.
When will this end?
Don't worry, My Lady ...
Her Highness might become disinterested in her
after a few days and return her to your care.
Will she?
She cries all day and all night.
How am I supposed to sleep?
May peace be restored in Your Highness.
Bring the nursemaids here.
I need to know how they pacify her.
Yes.
Don't cry.
How are the two of you taking care of her?
I cannot sleep at all when she keeps crying.
Your Highness, we've tried everything.
The princess might need more time to get used to
an unfamiliar chamber since her mother is away.
Sorry to have disturbed Your Highness.
Did you really do everything you can?
I'm sorry for my incompetence.
- Bring me the princess.
- Yes.
Oh, Wenyi, good girl, don't cry.
She's a lot of work.
- Song Zhi.
- Yes.
Bring my teapills for sleep, and a bowl of warm water.
Yes.
Faster!
Your Highness.
Here, good girl, have a spoon.
Your Highness, I'm afraid the princess
is too young to be taking such medicine.
Why? The medicine works fine on me.
If you dare say a word about it,
I will have your heads off.
We understand.
Now take her away.
Quickly.
(yawning)
Don't cry.
Now you know what to do if she keeps crying at night.
- Yes, Your Highness.
My Lady, Her Highness shows great care for
the princess only when His Majesty visits.
But Her Highness ignores her needs otherwise.
As nursemaids, we must have
low-sodium diets to produce good milk.
But no one keeps this in mind
since Her Highness pays no attention to us.
To make things worse, the princess did not like
our milk and kept crying at night.
Her Highness made the princess consume sedatives.
I'm afraid it will damage her health
to take such medicine at this age.
But what can I do?
She rarely allowed me to see Wenyi when I visited.
And she took offence if I asked about Wenyi,
saying that I should trust her.
I wouldn't know any of this if you didn't come to tell me.
My Lady, please think of a way to take back the princess.
How much I want that!
She is having her moment right now.
How would she let go?
I will do my best to take care of the princess.
Please don't worry for now, My Lady.
If the princess can return home,
we will be thankful to Amitābha Buddha.
Thank you.
You have dark circles under your eyes.
Did you not sleep well last night?
It's all right.
I saw Wenyi was sleepy today, not so playful as before.
Is she not feeling well?
I entreat Your Majesty's forgiveness for
my failure to take care of the princess.
It is very difficult to look after such a young child.
You should send her back to Lady Cao.
Lady Cao was feeling unwell and sent Wenyi to my care.
I'm afraid it will affect Lady Cao's health
if I send Wenyi back right now.
Your Majesty, the princess cried a lot at night
and thus was sleepy during the day.
Her Highness had to take care of her all night.
That is why Her Highness's eyes are red.
I appreciate your hard work. Rise.
I thank Your Majesty.
It is natural for a young child to be prone to crying.
But in my view, yin is too strong
when women dominantly reside in the palace.
That will disturb the young princess at night.
If we have yang to balance with yin ...
Today is the 16th of the month.
I will stay here to appreciate the moon with you.
Tell Lady Sourire that she should sleep early.
Your Majesty might want to try the turtle-crane longevity soup.
[Turtles and cranes are the symbols for longevity.
In fact, the soup uses chicken instead of crane.]
Wenyi is quiet tonight.
Like I said, Your Majesty's yang counteracts the excess yin in her chamber.
That's why she stopped crying.
What was that?
It's just thunder, Your Majesty.
We should sleep.
My Lady, are you all right?
My Lady, you've always been
frightened of thunder since you were young.
Her Ladyship would always be there for you.
His Majesty would usually visit on a thundering night.
Would you like my company for tonight?
At this very moment,
Consort Fleur must be softly whispering to His Majesty.
Too much has happened recently.
I'm exhausted.
I understand.
You should go sleep. I'll have some time to myself.
Huan Huan ...
it's me.
Si Lang.
I was wakened by thunder, thinking that
you must be scared on such a stormy night.
Si Lang, you shouldn't have walked through the wind and rain.
I wouldn't leave you feeling scared of the storm.
You shouldn't worry about me
when I'm away out of your sight.
My heart sees what my eyes don't.
What about Her Highness?
Si Lang, will you always be so good to me?
I will.
Your words always bring peace to my mind.
Your Highness, His Majesty has been away for so long.
Your Highness might as well sleep for now.
His Majesty was never like this.
He was never like this.
Your Highness.
May peace be restored in Your Highness.
She'll die.
Your Majesty, His Majesty left the Cooling Hall
and walked to Verdant Reading Hall in the rain.
Consort Fleur has had her day.
A new fire burns higher than the old flame.
Consort Fleur can now feast on the same humiliation I experienced.
When His Majesty visited you, Consort Fleur would try
every trick in the book to make him leave.
But this time, His Majesty chose to leave.
It's no use keeping His Majesty for the night
when you can't keep his heart.
The Governor of Guangdong and Guangxi Provinces
presented me with a mandarin duck folding screen.
[Mandarin ducks are believed to be lifelong couples.]
I'll give it to Lady Sourire.
Yes.
What incense did you light in the censer?
I lit sandalwood when I saw Your Majesty
chanting on such a humid night.
Homage to the Buddha is not paid by the incense we burn.
Even the finest incense is artificially produced
and carries a whiff from the secular world.
I prefer the natural scents from flowers and fruits.
You may put it away.
[contact translators] carsenwei@yahoo.com
[subscribe on homepage] liberapay.com/ZHZSubbers
My Lady, Companion An is here.
Sourire.
Lingrong.
I spent a few days embroidering the blue satin you gave to me.
I hope you'll like it.
I felt that instead of embroidering a winter crow
in wait for imperial favor,
I'd rather it be the peach blossoms graced by the spring showers.
I believe it is time to bring your thoughtfulness to its fruition.
"The vibrant peach tree is afire with its brilliant blooms;"
[Quoting Tao Yao from the Classic of Poetry]
"Fragrant as the young bride
who sweetens her husband’s home."
Thank you for your kind words.
Allow me to choose clothing and ornaments for you.
Mm.
Come.
This seems appropriate. What do you think?
Your dress is bright as the rosy clouds.
It makes me blush.
Brighter colors might be more appropriate for your status,
but a cool color is a delight to the eyes on a hot summer day.
"A lotus out of water is refreshingly unadorned."
Let's go.
Peace to My Ladies.
Look, there's a pair of mandarin ducks.
It's an auspicious sign.
Sourire, I'm nervous.
Should we think of something else?
If I present you to His Majesty in an ordinary way,
that would be acceptable
but His Majesty might forget you after a few days.
It would hinder you from your future advancement.
Zhongyuan [Ghost Festival] is an important festival in the palace.
We must be prepared for the rituals.
Certainly.
Princess Wenyi has not been very well.
I will tell the priests to pray for her.
"Cherish not your gold-woven robe, in truth.
Cherish but your golden days of youth."
Who is singing?
It might be a performer in the palace.
Such a beautiful voice is a rarity in the palace.
"Cull the flower in its full bloom,
not the empty branch you’d carry with gloom."
Sourire.
Your voice is inebriating.
You must not make fun of me.
Who was singing?
Peace to Your Highness.
You may rise.
Yes.
When did you learn to sing, Lady Sourire?
I'm surprised by your talent for both singing and dancing.
I'm not the one to be praised by Your Highness.
I could never sing so well.
It was Companion An.
I was wondering who it was.
It turns out that it is the daughter of An Bihuai,
who has just been pardoned for his crime.
How dare the daughter of a former convict
act so ostentatiously in public?
What shamelessness!
My father did not commit any crime.
Companion An's father was released and reinstated after his acquittal.
He did not offend His Majesty.
Being acquitted doesn't mean he is not guilty at all.
I need not remind Lady Sourire why he was released.
Since this Companion does not know how to behave,
you must teach her proper decorum and good morality.
She was simply singing a song.
That does not concern decorum or morality.
"Cull the flower in its full bloom ..."
Flower is known as a metaphor for women.
So this line implies she would like to
"attract the bees and butterflies"
and she is ready to be culled.
The song is titled "The Gold-Woven Robe".
It advises us to cherish time more than gold.
Your Highness misinterpreted the line.
Lady Sourire is an eloquent speaker indeed.
Unfortunately, obedience rather than sophistry
is the traditional virtue of women.
What defiance of feminine virtues it is to offend your superior!
I dare not.
Lady Sourire had no intention to offend Your Highness.
I beg Your Highness's pardon.
Isn't it too late to beg for pardon
once an offence has been committed?
As the head of His Majesty's consorts,
I will spare no effort in enforcing the rules of the palace.
-Somebody, come!
-Yes.
Grace to Your Majesties.
That was very beautiful singing.
I rarely see you wearing bright colors.
You may rise.
You look a little unhappy today?
I cannot tolerate the singing of a decadent song in broad daylight.
You tell me ... How was the singing?
Companion An has a celestial voice.
I'm unworthy of Your Majesty's commendation.
"A snap of the Kunlun Jade; a dewdrop on the cotton rose"
could barely compare with the beauty of her voice.
Raise your head.
I like the line "cull the flower in its full bloom".
What is your name?
An Lingrong.
You must say "Your Majesty" in your responses.
I humbly thank Your Highness for the advice.
Consort Fleur will have many more
opportunities to talk to Companion An.
You'll have plenty of time to teach her in the future.
Of course I will.
Managing the palace is like sorting tangled threads.
I must carry some of the burden for Your Majesty.
Very well, you are as beautiful as your voice.
Your Majesty, I'm feeling a bit tired.
May I take my leave?
Certainly.
Vermilion, take care of Lady Sourire.
Yes.
I will go with Sourire.
I enjoyed her song very much.
I hope she will sing again for me and Your Majesty.
Please ask Companion An to come back.
Yes.
Sourire, I'll see you later.
Have some rest and be prepared for serving His Majesty tonight.
My Ladies, may I have your attention?
Yes, sir.
His Majesty would like Companion An to come back.
Go quickly.
You should go now.
Mm.
Your Majesty, Companion An is here.
Your Majesty.
Come walk with me.
I need to talk to Consort Fleur about the Zhongyuan Festival.
I'm afraid I can't accompany Your Majesty for the rest of the day.
If you say so.
Consort Fleur, shall we?
Do you wish to go home now, My Lady?
Let's have a walk along the lake.
My Lady, you look gorgeous in this dress.
You used to not wear red,
but what a beautiful color it is!
It looks like the rosy clouds.
And it's embroidered with crabapple flowers, your favorite!
Of course, the palace has embroidery of the highest quality.
Thousands and thousands of threads and stitches ...
Beauty is knitted with so much effort.
Each thread is essential and every stitch is necessary.
Vermilion, the needle is so sharp.
Did the satin hurt when the needle pierced it?
My Lady, why would you think about that?
To create embroidery, the satin has to be pierced by the needle.
But the satin is not a person.
It doesn't feel any pain.
My Lady, look at the thriving lotus flowers.
How beautiful they are!
Look ...
Yes, the lotus flowers are so beautiful.
It's no longer the season for crabapple flowers.
Cherish not your gold-woven robe, in truth.
Cherish but your golden days of youth.
Cull the flower in its full bloom,
not the empty branch you’d carry with gloom.
I thank Your Majesty.
Peace to Noble Prince Guo.
Rise.
Is His Majesty inside?
He invited me to play Go with him.
I'm afraid it's not a good time.
I heard that there's another Lady Melodic,
who has an even more beautiful voice.
It is Companion An.
I thought it was Lady Sourire.
Lady Sourire has been with His Majesty most of the time.
But that might be different from now on.
I see. I should have come at a convenient time.
Tomorrow, please tell His Majesty that I came.
-Yes.
-Goodbye.
I bid Your Lordship goodbye.
I'm going to schedule night shifts.
You're back, My Lady.
Congratulations, My Lady.
Stand up quickly.
I was waiting for the announcement of your arrival,
My Lady, but I didn't hear anything.
I should have come back in a carriage.
But I preferred to take a walk by myself.
And here I am.
My Lady, why would you take the trouble to walk?
I have always walked looking down with caution.
Now I have truly become a concubine.
I was wondering how it would feel to walk in the palace now.
That's why I preferred to walk.
How was your trip walking back, My Lady?
I used to keep my eyes on the road.
But today I discovered the pleasantness of
the trees and flowers in the palace.
My Lady, you don't seem to be happy
about Companion An's advancement.
There's no surprise in an anticipated event.
My Lady, Companion An is here.
Sourire.
Why did you come so early in the morning?
I have just paid my respects to the Empress.
I was thinking that I should visit you.
Companion An is different now.
You used to not visit My Lady every day.
The Maple Dew tea has been steeped for three times.
Please bring some to Companion An.
Sourire, do you blame me?
Why would I?
Nothing would make me happier than seeing you in favor.
And we spared no effort to make this happen.
Why would I blame you for anything?
Sourire, if it caused you any uneasiness,
I shall not see His Majesty again.
You're talking like a child.
I am the matchmaker in a sense.
A matchmaker only hopes the bride and groom will see each other again.
You'd always make fun of me.
Good to know that you don't blame me.
The color of your dress really flatters your skin tone.
It's made of the tributary Glinting Satin from Suzhou Province.
They say it shimmers in motion under the sun.
I really like its color so I put it on.
I remember that only a few pieces of
Glinting Satin are offered each year.
His Majesty rewarded them all to you, didn't he?
Yes, he did.
But I dare not keep all of them.
I only saved one piece for myself.
Two were given to the Empress and Consort Fleur.
And I wish you would keep the other two pieces.
Thank you for thinking of me.
It's my pleasure.
They say the Glinting Satin was offered as tribute by
the Kingdom of Gaochang in the Tang Dynasty.
It wouldn't get wet in the rain.
Now that we are able to produce it in Suzhou,
I wonder if it's truly water-resistant.
I will try it on when it rains.
Mm.
This is strange.
Lingrong hasn't visited for a couple of days.
Who would come out in such sultry weather?
The Empress even waived our daily visits.
That's true.
As long as His Majesty still comes here.
It's all right for My Lady think like that.
Why are you looking forward to His Majesty's visits?
Don't say that! I'm not!
You are! You are!
My Lady would be unhappy if she hears it.
- But you are!
- I'm not! Stop it!
Madam.
Girls, My Lady is inside.
It's inappropriate to be so loud should His Majesty visit.
Madam, where are you heading to with the food box?
My Lady sends me to visit Attendant An.
She was worried that Attendant An might feel unwell in the heat.
She asked me to give her some preventive medicine.
My Lady cares more about her than Vermillion and me.
Jade, that's enough.
You must not talk like that.
Yes, Madam.
She is an Attendant now while we are just her maids.
Jade has been volatile in her tempers lately.
Jade was spoiled by My Lady at home.
She was treated like her sister.
She's been working lazily these days.
I can't find her sometimes.
I will let My Lady know about her misbehavior.
Madam, please don't take it personally.
It's all right.
I didn't really mind. You can go.
Yes.
I need to ask you something.
Lingrong didn't offend you.
Why do you always treat her this way?
My Lady, don't you think that snob is trying to show off?
She came here wearing her glinting dress and glittering hairpins.
As if we'd never seen such things before!
Stop!
I simply asked you one question
and you filled my room with complaints.
She is the new favorite of His Majesty.
Do you think she should hide the rewards in her pockets?
But My Lady, she was always receiving gifts from you.
Look what she has now ...
No matter what she has,
she is a concubine of His Majesty.
Remember your status.
Don't look for trouble!
I understand.
You must stop being petulant.
I saved one of the dresses made of Glinting Satin for you.
Remember not to flaunt it.
I won't.
The Imperial Kitchen made some water chestnut cakes.
I'm craving one.
I'll bring it here immediately, My Lady!
[contact translators] carsenwei@yahoo.com
[subscribe on homepage] liberapay.com/ZHZSubbers
Theme: The Lonely Phoenix
[phoenix is the symbol of an empress]
I dimly recall the colorful blooms in every summer.
They are as distant as the autumn moon in the water.
He loved me with a volatile heart.
And before I knew it, we fell apart.
Behind me are the promises and longing.
Before me lie the flute and the zither.
I loved you with my body and soul
But you hurt me from head to toe.
My wish ran athwart
and I ended up a fool of my destiny.
My love was the wind-swept flowers from a tree.
A plum bloomed in winter hoping for a fruitful summer.
But the irresistible winds of destiny destroyed her wish.
You can hear the flapping of a phoenix
but you will never see it.
What you see is the falling leaves from the phoenix tree.
The falling leaves from the phoenix tree.